



VIET DANG, MBA

506 Winding Wood Dr., Wetumpka, AL 36093





(713) 582-7317 vdang@veedang.com /veedang



SENIOR TECHNOLOGY AND INFRASTRUCTURE EXECUTIVE

ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS ARCHITECT | APPLICATION SECURITY ARCHITECT | BUSINESS SYSTEMS INTELLIGENCE

Senior technology advisor, cybersecurity expert, and architecture leader with MBA, bachelor's in IT, and more than 25 years' combined experience planning, launching, and managing technology divisions and projects, IT organizations, and client support services. Proficiencies include solution analysis, workflow design strategies, technology advancements, and business continuity. Exhibits flexibility to adapt to emerging business realities, maximizes human capital ingenuity and pride, and drives productivity, revenues, and profits. Takes on fleet management, financing, and any other division in need of strong leadership to increase ROI. Introspective, insightful, diligent, and approachable. GSLC, PMP, and CSM certified.

LEADERSHIP

- Vision Setting/Development
- Human Capital Management
- CEO and Client Guidance
- P&L Ownership/Budget Driver
- Process/Quality Champion
- Intuitive Team Builder/Inspires Loyalty

TECHNOLOGY

- Industry Awareness
- Technical Cohesion and Scalability
- SaaS/PaaS/IaaS/Cloud Development
- Solution & Data Architecture
- Infrastructure Efficiency Expert
- Technology Innovation

KNOWLEDGE

- Rigorous Compliance Best Practices
- Business Intelligence
- Cybersecurity Management
- Technical Translations
- Risk Analysis and Risk Mitigation
- Business Continuity/Disaster Planning

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2017 - Present

Southern Poverty Law Center

Montgomery, AL

Director, Information Technology

Figurehead and executive strategist for all information technology processes, systems, tools, and data science initiatives, including governance of \$5M budget and 25-person division. Transformed team without any previous leadership, best practices standards, or established processes by installing processes, protocols, change management, and emergency preparedness, response, and disaster recovery plans. Removed silos, eliminated compartmentalization mindset, developed transparency in reporting, outlined and implemented solid communication practices, and developed project planning and management workflows that achieved twentyfold better communication and credibility making IT now a go-to authority and trusted source.

- > Trusted Advisor: Operate as security SME. Crafted and implemented first-ever P&Ps and records retention policy, make recommendations/brainstorm with CEO to expand security footprint and guide long-range planning, and act as major influencer on strategic next steps across PCI SSC and special interest groups
- > Technical Leader: Executive architecture strategist holding go/no-go authority over all technical decisions, procurement, and \$2M purchase and implementation of AI mechanism to track demographics after migrating CRM system to new host; authorized and guided rollout of new helpdesk ticketing system that brought customer satisfaction to 99.998%
- > Cybersecurity Expert: Lead knowledge management and prevention of security risks and risk mitigation, oversee change management and incident response programs, access controls, strategies and communications related to defense posture, OPSEC principles, and privacy policy execution, IT ethics, IP protections, cryptography, and network infrastructure
- > Service Enhancements: Direct deepened understanding of audience profiles through extraction and translation of intelligence gathered across all communication channels, allowing direct reports to use gathered information to explore new approaches from trending conversation insights, while gaining meaningful, real-time grasp of what matters
- > Standards Alignment: Document long term vision, technical specifications, integration plans, deployment strategies, and maintenance lifecycle processes; create unified suite of scalable, enduring processes that illustrate the way forward
- Lessons Learned: Conduct post-mortem debriefings with teams to review operational metrics and identify what was missed, where process blocks arose, and what issues surfaced; track project pulse, response times, and resolution success
- > Take-Charge Leadership: Conducted weekly debriefing engagements with division leads and key personnel to review operational metrics and identify what was missed, where process blocks arose, and what customer-issue themes surfaced; tracked dispatched afterhours requests, customer temperatures, response times, and resolution success; prepared reports, hosted and participated in strategy meetings, and resolved tactical roadblocks

Director, IT Operations

Directed management of two technical divisions (application development and infrastructure) serving internal customers across 20 sites globally, including Dubai and Singapore. Governance included project management, service desk and support, media services, technical intelligence, expansion planning, business continuity, and cybersecurity programs. Led evaluation of new sites for operations and datacenters, governed IT and telecom operations and globally distributed service delivery, managed stringent annual OpEx and CapEx budget of \$1.5MM, oversaw execution of vendor agreements, guided RFPs, and commanded infrastructure and security for live and virtualized servers, cloud storage, and service enhancements.

- ➤ <u>Metric Wins:</u> Leveraged knowledge strengthen infrastructure during transitions; designed and executed six new IT spaces, including telephony, cabling, number of racks, circuit terminations, relocation of three datacenters and consolidation down to one, and countless office moves with zero downtime and zero formal complaints raised
- > <u>Business Acumen:</u> Accelerated SLAs across all service lines and mature teams and organizational structure to generate rapid and sustainable growth for technical efforts and needs; managed C-suite relationships, and displace roadblocks through consistency and superior service delivery achieving **morale upticks of more than 130%**
- ➤ <u>Reliability:</u> Transformed nonexistent customer service initiatives and quality control processes by integrating KPI-based, metric driven management; guided pipeline engineers to re-invent workflow processes for strategic priorities to sweeping success: reduced trouble ticket time frequently exceeding 24 hours or more to 80% resolved in less than 1 hour
- ➤ <u>Human Capital:</u> Leveraged industry intelligence to head business case and service roadmap development; attracted/ built/retained cohesive, highly-productive team through adoption and implementation of industry proven best practices
- ➤ <u>Project Management:</u> Implemented Epicor Vantage and Great Plains ERP systems for N. America; developed actionable program plans, oversaw requirements' backlog, produced risk and budget analyses, led day-to-day operations, and delivered enterprise solutions that enabled data visualization and collaboration across globally distributed environment

2002 – 2006 NSPOF Communications, Inc. Houston, TX

Systems Consultant (CIO)

Designed and architected infrastructure, system, and network solutions for technical operations, software migrations, and integration and development of all business accounts; scoped services, gathered and quantified requirements, established delivery timelines, and worked with top tier manufacturers such as Cisco, 3COMM, and HP to execute and manage to plan. Spearheaded software development, infrastructure/system, and business continuity teams, led proposal development and presentations, created escalation procedures, forecasted client needs for on-point SLA fulfillment, and performed consumer business process analysis for ERP implementations and continuity planning.

- > <u>Subject Matter Expert:</u> Performed as SME on connectivity, network design, system architecture, scalability, performance, change management, product installations, and emergency preparedness/redundancies
- > <u>Authored:</u> Quantified and drafted operations' roadmaps and specifications, team integration plans, technology deployment strategies, phased server virtualization plans, and maintenance of server life cycles
- > <u>Standards Base-lining:</u> Pioneered security risk assessment-resolution policies that identified and corrected vulnerabilities, exploitation, and configuration errors, architected and implemented robust cybersecurity defenses against unauthorized entry, misuse, fraud, and attacks, and increased quality of deliverables by reducing error rate through use of KPIs

2001 – 2002 Cooperheat-MQS Houston, TX

Director, Information Technology

Oversaw 24/7 support services providing onsite and remote guidance to resolve end-user and technical team issues. Hired, trained, and mentored employees, executed skill development classes to increase performance speed and satisfaction surveys, created testing procedures to assess proficiencies, and resolved escalated issues. Marshalled resources and focused energy and attention on critical points and highest priorities. Became knowledge manager after authoring documents and processes for projects and establishing network standards. Worked cross-divisionally to reduce labor and productivity costs, and improve financial reporting and forecasting both quarterly and annually.

- ➤ <u>Technical Leadership:</u> Investigated, tested, proposed, configured, and implemented Great Plains ERP system to great acclaim and increased morale due to reduced multiple entry efforts on legacy MRP systems; established compliance practices, implemented module owners' program, evaluated projections and capacity planning, and initiated all protocols
- > <u>Process Reengineering:</u> Established and enforced coding standards, adherence to design patterns, and always on-point documentation practices; authored proposals, feasibility analyses, workflow roadmaps, technical policy guidelines, requirements, and supervised technical systems audits to ensure robust productivity, scalability, and efficiencies
- > <u>Cybersecurity:</u> Lead information risk management and mitigation, threat intelligence, security operations, incident response, emergency preparedness, and disaster recovery planning as it related to IT operations, cybersecurity, and Tier 1 and Tier 2 technical services/customer support

VIET DANG 2 | Page

Director, Information Systems

Architected long term information technology, service, and vision, technical specifications of applications and integration plans, deployment strategies, and maintenance lifecycle processes; created unified suite of scalable, enduring strategies and business case examples to illustrate the way forward and aligned teams and processes that anchored them to tangible results.

- Leadership: Guided staff using agile, metric-driven methodologies, and earned-value leadership techniques; developed internal audit and sign-off protocols according to industry standards to meet IT audit compliance; led coordination for cross-disciplines to triage issues and develop or implement custom technology/tools that sped up resolution
- > <u>Seamless Service Delivery:</u> Performed as technical project lead for all large-scale infrastructure upgrades achieved with minimal downtime; directed support efforts for hosts, including predictive and reactive services, enhanced technical support (ETS), and custom technical support (CTS) and proactive oversight of change management best practices

1996 – 1999 USA Waste, Inc. Houston, TX

Information Technology Manager

Led design, maintenance, and configuration of network, including LAN/WAN, capacity planning/load balancing, and fault-tolerant, high availability server system. Conducted equipment evaluations, performance assessments, and generated executive-level reports to shape decision-making that directly affected end-users and firm's reputation.

- > Zero Excuses Uptime: Expanded and maintained redundancy network and protocols to span multi-site datacenters to guarantee 24/7/365 100% performance under all circumstances
- ➤ <u>Growth Infrastructure:</u> Revitalized and managed project and operations objectives to develop and support mission-critical 24/7 support for firm's user base; interfaced directly with senior management, and held oversight for all desktop support, security hardening, server management, and business applications

----- EDUCATION & TRAINING

Master of Business Administration, *International Business* (2009) | University of Houston-Victoria | Victoria, TX Bachelor of Science, *Information Technology* (2003) | American InterContinental University | Atlanta, GA Project Management Professional (PMP) (2006) | Project Management Institute

Certified ScrumMaster (CSM) (2017) | The Scrum Alliance

GIAC Security Leadership (GSLC) (2019) | Global Information Assurance Certification **US NAVY**, U.S.S. Independence (CV-62) – Navy Unit Commendation Medal, Navy Expeditionary Medal, Armed Forces Expeditionary Medal, Good Conduct Medal: Honorable Discharge



VIET DANG 3 | Page